Guide to the Elbert Peets Papers, 1883-1983, 1904-1974 (bulk)
Peets, Elbert Papers
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Elbert Peets papers, 1883-1983 1904-1974
2772
Elbert Peets, 1886-1968.
4.2 cubic ft.
Correspondence, reports, manuscripts, notes, family papers, clippings, photographs, negatives, plans, and drawings.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Includes correspondence, reports, clippings, photographs, plans, and drawings related to projects on which Peets worked; material on the L'Enfant plan for Washington, D.C., of which Peets was a major proponent and guardian; material related to articles and books by or about Peets, including photographs and negatives from the book Civic Art; and personal correspondence, notes, manuscripts, and family papers.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Elbert Peets received his B.A. from Western Reserve University and his M.L.A. from the Harvard University School of Landscape Architecture and City Planning. He worked for Pray, Hubbard and White, Boston landscape architects, for a year before joining with Werner Hegemann to plan Kohler, a company town founded by Walter S. Kohler, near Sheboygan, Wisconsin. Peets and Hegemann also collaborated in the planning of Washington Highlands, a subdivision in Milwaukee, Wisconsin; of Wyomissing Park, a subdivision in Reading, Pennsylvania; and in the writing of The American Vitruvius: An Architect's Handbook of Civic Art (1922). From 1923-1935 Peets worked in private practice in Cleveland, Ohio. He also worked on the planning for Greendale (near Milwaukee), one of three greenbelt towns built by the U.S. Farm Resettlement Administration headed by Rexford Guy Tugwell under Franklin D. Roosevelt. From 1938-1944 he was Chief of the Site Planning Section of the U.S. Housing Authority. With the firm of Loebl, Schlossman & Bennett, he participated in the planning for the town of Park Forest (near Chicago, Illinois), a project initiated by Nathan Manilow, Treasurer of American Community Builders, Inc., and Philip Klutznick, President. In the 1950s, Peets was a member of the Fine Arts Commission and served as consultant to the National Capital Park and Planning Commission.
Peets did site planning in Washington, D.C., lectured at Harvard and Yale, and served as consultant to several private planning firms. He also wrote numerous articles on planning and landscape architecture.
CHRONOLOGY
May 5, 1886 Born Cleveland Ohio to Edward Orville Peets and Mary Curetta Houghton Peets
Graduated from Central High School in Cleveland, Ohio
1912 B.A. magna cum laude, Western Reserve University; First Scholarship Honors, Phi Beta Kappa
Foreman for H.U. Horvath, landscape architect and nurseryman while in college
1915 M.L.A., Harvard University, School of Landscape Architecture and City Planning; instructed in horticulture at Harvard, 1914-1915
June 1915-June 1916 Worked for Pray, Hubbard and White, Landscape Architects, making plans for land subdivisions
June 1916-Jan. 1917 Worked with Werner Hegemann on Kohler, Wisconsin, a "company" town, in Sheboygan; Milwaukee, Wisconsin--subdivisions, parks, playground, cemeteries
Jan. 1917-Dec. 1918 Civilian Planning Engineer with the U.S. Army, Camp Planning Section, Construction Division. Made plans for: Hospitals (Staten Island, Colonia, Otisville, etc.); Remount Stations
Jan. 1919-Apr. 1920 In practice with Werner Hegemann on: Washington Highlands, large subdivision in Milwaukee, Wisconsin
Apr. 1920-Mar. 1921 Charles Eliot Traveling Fellowship: London, Paris, Rome, Vienna, Berlin, Amsterdam
Apr. 1921-May 1922 Continued practice with Werner Hegemann; collaborated with Hegemann in writing Civic Art: The American Vitruvius
June 1922-June 1923 Wyomissing Park, large subdivision including areas for working people, Reading, Pennsylvania
July 1923-July 1933 Private practice in Cleveland, Ohio; work included gardens, parks, land subdivisions; also wrote articles
July 1933-Nov. 1933 Cleveland City Planning Commission; parks, playgrounds, civic improvements
Nov. 1933-Apr. 1934 U.S. Department of Agriculture; layout of roads and other site planning work at Beltsville, Maryland; representative of A.D. Taylor, President of ASLA
May 1934-Nov. 1935 Private practice in Cleveland; writing
Nov. 1935-Feb. 1938 U.S. Farm Resettlement Administration in Washington; principal town planner for Greendale, Wisconsin
Feb. 1938-Apr. 1939 Catalina Island, California; plans and report on the future development of the Wrigley Estate and the town of Avalon
Apr. 1938-1944 Chief of Site Planning Section, U.S. Housing Authority, and Federal Public Housing Authority
1939 Report on City Planning and Housing for San Juan, Puerto
1941 Report for the National Resources Planning Board (NRPB): "An Interior Program of Planning Studies for the Physical Development of Puerto Rico" (with Hale Walker and Tracy Augur)
1944 Lectured at the New York Museum of National History on Aerial Urban Reconnaissance and Site Recognition
1945 Consultant in Town Planning for FPHA and USHA
1945-1948 Prepared plans for the extension of Greendale; drafted a zoning ordinance for Greendale
1945-1951 Housing consultant and site planner for the Municipal Housing Authority of San Juan, Puerto Rico
1946-1947 Site and City Planner for Phillip Klutznick, American Community Builders, Park Forest, Illinois
1950-1954 Member of the Fine Arts Commission, Washington
1951-1953 Consultant to the National Capital Park and Planning Commission
1950-1960 Lecturer at Yale and Harvard; consultant to several private planning firms; Harland Bartholomew; McGaughan and Johnson; plan for the S.W. Washington Redevelopment with Louis Justement
1951-1962 Worked with sculptor Felix de Weldon on site planning for memorials: Plaza Bolivar, Washington, D.C.; monument to General Calixto Garcia, Havana, Cuba; Pershing Memorial, Washington, D.C.; Stone Mountain Memorial, Atlanta, Georgia; National War Memorial, Kuala Lumpur, Malaysia
1963 Site plan for U.S. National Arboretum, Washington, D.C.
1964-1968 Health problems prevented further work
Mar. 26, 1968 Died in Austinburg, Ohio
This sketch was largely done by Paul Spreiregen, editor of On the Art of Designing Cities (1968), a collection of Elbert Peets' writings. Several additions and corrections have been made since the arranging of the Elbert Peets Papers.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Includes correspondence, reports, clippings, photographs, plans, and drawings related to projects on which Peets worked; material on the L'Enfant plan for Washington, D.C., of which Peets was a major proponent and guardian; material related to articles and books by or about Peets, including photographs and negatives from the book Civic Art; and personal correspondence, notes, manuscripts, and family papers.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Peets, Elbert, 1886-1968.; Peets, Edward Orville.; Peets, Mary Euretta Houghton.; Hegemann, Werner.; Kohler, Walter S.; Tugwell, Rexford G. (Rexford Guy), 1891-; Manilow, Nathaniel.; Klutznick, Philip M.; L'Enfant, Pierre Charles, 1754-1825.; Peets, Elbert, 1886-1968. American Vetruvius: an architect's handbook of civic art.; Pray, Hubbard, and White.; United States. Farm Resettlement Administration.; United States. Housing Authority. Site Planning Section.; United States. Federal Public Housing Authority.; Loebl, Schlosman & Bennett.; American Community Builders, Inc.; United States. Commission of Fine Arts.; United States. National Capital Park and Planning Commission.
Subjects:
Landscape architecture.; City planning.; Landscape architects.; City planners.
Places:
Cleveland (Ohio)--City planning.; Boston (Mass.)--City planning.; Kohler (Wis.)--City planning.; Washington Highlands (Milwaukee, Wis.)--City planning.; Wyomissing Park (Reading, Pa.)--City planning.; Greendale (Pa.)--City planning.; Park Forest (Ill.)--City planning.; Washington (D.C.)--City planning.
Form and Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Drawings.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
COLLECTION ARRANGEMENT
This collection consists of three 16" boxes and three 5" boxes of papers, two oversize bound volumes, and one mapcase drawer of oversize plans and drawings. There was no discernible original order to the collection, so its present arrangement is entirely imposed.
The five boxes of papers are arranged under three subject headings. The first is Projects, Appointments and Consultations. It runs from Box 1 Folder 1 to Box 1 Folder 53, and contains papers relating to the major projects undertaken by Peets as outlined in the biographical sketch. A significant amount of material on the L'Enfant plan of Washington, D.C. is included; Peets was a major proponent and guardian of this original plan throughout his life.
Projects in the first subject area are arranged in chronological order, but with some overlap; within each project papers are arranged by item type (correspondence, writings, clippings, photos, plans and drawings) and chronologically within each type. Not all projects or appointments contain all record types.
The second subject heading is Peets' Writings, and is subdivided into published and unpublished sections. Material relating to newspaper and magazine articles and books are included in the published section, which goes from Box 1 Folder 54 to Box 2 Folder 89. A large number of negatives and prints from the book Civic Art (1922), which Peets co-authored with Werner Hegemann, is contained in this section. Also included are papers relating to the publication of On the Art of Designing Cities (1968), Paul D. Spreiregen, editor, a collection of selected essays of Elbert Peets. The rest of the writings in the section, both published and unpublished, deal with site and city planning, landscape architecture, and civic art. Unpublished writings run from Box 2 Folder 90 to Box 3 Folder 14.
The third subject category is General Papers, Box 3 Folder 15 to Box 5 Folder 13. This category contains personal materials, papers relating to minor projects and items not directly related to the two previous categories. It is divided into sections by record type and is arranged chronologically within each section. The ten sections are correspondence, notes, manuscripts, pamphlets, clippings, brochures, photos, graphics, family and biographical material, and miscellaneous papers. The quantity of personal correspondence is fairly small but helps give an impression of Peets' character and interests. Box 3 Folder 63 contains a number of photographs of Peets. The section of graphics is divided into several subsections: estates, perspectives, plans and elevations, sketches, sketchbooks and lineoleum prints. There are a variety of types (original pencil or pen and ink drawings, blueprints, photostats, etc.), but they have in common that they are not immediately recognizable as belonging with one of the major projects in the first subject category. The last subsection of the Graphics section contains miscellaneous non-Peets graphic items. The biographical material under the third subject heading largely repeats the information in the biographical sketch, but a few more details may be found here. The folder of family material (Box 5, Folder 12) contains a xerox copy of the last will and testament of Hiram Houghton, Elbert Peets' maternal grandfather. Also included is a xerox copy of a notebook of Edward O. Peets, Elbert's father, in which he kept notes on his readings.
The two oversize bound volumes in the collection are a copy of the book Civic Art and a scrapbook containing a number of original pencil and pen and ink drawings by Elbert Peets.
The oversize plans, prints, and original drawings in the mapcase drawer were either done by Peets or relate to his projects. There are 342 pieces in 19 folders divided as follows:
School projects--Folder 1
Town and city plans--Folders 2-7
Private residence and estates--Folders 8-11
Memorials, parks, and recreation areas--Folders 12-14
Other projects--Folders 15-19
See the guide for specific date ranges and piece counts in each category. The drawings are arranged in chronological order within each subject and project.
ELBERT PEETS' WRITINGS
Partial List of Published Articles by Elbert Peets:
Practical Tree Repair; the physical repair of trees - bracing and the treating of wounds and cavities. McBride, Nast and Co., 1913.
"Civic Art - The American Vitruvius" by Hegemann & Peets, 1922 (Peets did many drawings and wrote the last chapter (VII) on Washington, D. C.)
1
"Central Park" American Mercury 4:339-341, March 1925
2
"Interior of the Lincoln Memorial" American Mercury 5:194-196, June 1925
3
"The New Washington" American Mercury 8:449-452, August 1926
4
"Mussolini, Haussmann and Company" New Republic 45:295-296, February 3, 1926
5
"Landscape Priesthood" American Mercury 10:94-100, January 1927
6
"Restoration of Rome" Catholic World 124:451-456, January 1927
7
"Cleveland Reservoir" The Nation 124:145, February 9, 1927 (Also in American City 36:825-826, June 1927)
8
"Reign of the Masonry Dome" The Nation 124:632-633, June 8, 1927
9
"The Genealogy of L'Enfant's Washington" (3 Parts) AIA Journal Part I XV:115-119 April 1927, Part II XV:151-154 May 1927, Part III XV:187-191 June 1927 (A condensed version of these appeared in "Der Staedtebau", Berlin Heft 11, 1928)
10
A series of four articles called "Famous Town Planners" The Town Planning Review University of Liverpool 1. "Camillo Sitte" December 1927 pp. 249-259 2. "Haussmann" June 1927 pp. 181-190 3. "L'Enfant" July 1928 pp. 30-49 4. "Wren" (On the rebuilding of London 1666) May 1930 pp. 13-30
11
A series on the L'Enfant Plan for Washington Baltimore Sunday Sun (under H. L. Mencken) 1. "The Ancestry of the L'Enfant Plan" February 10, 1929 2. "The New Washington" January 26, 1930 3. "The Lost Plazas of Washington" April 24, 1932 4. "New Plans for the Mall" March 3, 1935
12
"Current Town Planning in Washington" Town Planning Review 219-237 December 1931
13
"An Accurate Re-Drawing of the Central Part of L'Enfant's Autograph Plan" Architectural Record 72:158-160 September 1932
14
"L'Enfant's Washington" Town Planning Review 155-164 May 1933
15
"City Planner Believes (Architects) Pope Did Job He Was Supposed to Do" The Washington Daily News p. 10 April 7, 1937
16
"Washington, Williamsburg, the Century of Progress, and Greendale" from "City Planning, Housing" Werner Hegemann pp. 383-416 1937
17
"The Original Plan for Washington" House and Garden 78:16-19, 52, 61 July 1940
18
"Post-War Use of Temporary Sites" American City 58:49-50 November 1943
19
"Studies in Planning Texture" Architectural Record 106:130-137 Summer 1949
20
"The Genealogy of the Plan of Washington" Journal of the Society of American Architectural Historians X 2:3-4 May 1951
21
"The Golden Horses" City Planning at Yale (Book) 1954
22
"East Front Pilgrims" The Washington Post Letter to the Editor 1958 (no exact date)
23
"The President's Square" The Washington Post Letter to the Editor October 1961 (no exact date)
24
Article on L'Enfant in French Information et Documents (USIS Magazine) April 15, 1962
25
List of Reports by Elbert Peets:
"Landscape Development" U.S. Housing Authority Bulletin on Policy and Procedure. Date Uncertain.
1
"City Planning and Housing for San Juan" 1939
2
"Approach to Planting and the Selection of Plant Materials" A monograph on the design of low rental housing projects. U.S. Housing Authority - Federal Works Agency. July 1940
3
"An Interim Program of Planning - Studies for the Physical Development of Puerto Rico" With Tracy Augur and Hale Walker, National Resources Planning Board (MRPB) Charles W. Eliot, Director, 1941.
4
"'Comments' on the Neighborhood Concept" ASPO Bulletin
5
"Preliminary Indoctrination for Officials Enforcing the Old Georgetown Law" Fine Arts Commission, early 1950s.
6
Other Possible Material by Elbert Peets - the following pieces are referred to in various papers of Mr. Peets, but they have not yet been found:
Reference is made to an article in the American Mercury prior to 1922.
1
Reference is made to an exchange of letters to the editor between Peets and Lewis Mumford over Mumford's book The Brown Decades. This exchange took place in "The New Republic" about 1930-1931.
2
Mr. Peets sent comments on Adams' Regional Plan for New York and on articles by Mumford et. al. to W. Doregill, then editor of the "Town Planning Review" about July 1932.
3
SERIES LIST
Series I. Projects, Appointments, and Consultations
Box 1, Folder 1 - Box 1, Folder 53
Series II. Writings
Box 1, Folder 54 - Box 3, Folder 14
Series III. General Papers
Box 3, Folder 15 - Box 5, Folder 13
Series IV. Oversize Plans, Prints, and Drawings
Mapcase, Folders 1-19
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. Projects, Appointments, and Consultations
  - U.S. Army, Camp Planning Section certificate, list, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Washington Highlands (Milwaukee, Wisconsin) site plan pamphlets from Richter, Dick, and Reuterman, 1920 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Charles Eliot Traveling Fellowship, Harvard University Fellowship correspondence, invoices, 1917-1921 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Wyomissing Park, Pennsylvania - site plan correspondence, pamphlets, photos, drawings, map., 1921-1923 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - The L'Enfant Plan of Washington, correspondence, lists, 1925-1956 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - The L'Enfant Plan of Washington, unpublished manuscript, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 6-7)
  - The L'Enfant Plan of Washington, unpublished manuscript, lists, 1918-1919, 1961, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - The L'Enfant Plan of Washington, unpublished manuscript "Washington's Golden Age", n.d., Sept. 1934 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - The L'Enfant Plan of Washington, memoranda including American Planning and Civic Association, 1934, 1956, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - The L'Enfant Plan of Washington, letters of Pierre Charles L'Enfant, 1791 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - The L'Enfant Plan of Washington, pamphlets, 1924-1944 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - The L'Enfant Plan of Washington, articles, petition, report, 1924-1962 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - The L'Enfant Plan of Washington, clippings, 1952-1954 and n.d. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - The L'Enfant Plan of Washington, photos, 1922-1962, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - The L'Enfant Plan of Washington, drawings, sketches, plans, 1932-1951, nd.d (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - The L'Enfant Plan of Washington, drawings, plans, 1929-1956, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Paul V. Harper Estate landscaping, correspondence, 1928-1956 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Paul V. Harper Estate landscaping, correspondence (Box 1, Folder 19-20)
  - Paul V. Harper Estate landscaping, photos, c. 1928-1940 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Paul V. Harper Estate landscaping, drawings, sketches, c. 1928-1940 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Tent-house Construction, correspondence, plans, elevations, reports., 1933-1935 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Greendale, Wisconsin - town plan, Greenbelt towns correspondence, chart, 1935-1960 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Greendale, Wisconsin - town plan report, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Greendale, Wisconsin - town plan reports, proposed zoning ordinance, 1944-1960 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Greendale, Wisconsin - town plan manuscript articles by Peets, 1936, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Greendale, Wisconsin - town plan manuscript articles, 1936, 1959, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Greendale, Wisconsin - town plan articles, 1936-1959 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Greendale, Wisconsin - town plan pamphlets, 1936-1959, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Greendale, Wisconsin - town plan clippings, 1935-1967 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Greendale, Wisconsin - town plan photos (Box 1, Folder 32-34)
  - Greendale, Wisconsin - town plan maps, drawings, plans, 1936-1960 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Catalina Island, California - planned development correspondence, report, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Site Planning Section, U.S. Housing Authority and Federal Public Housing Authority correspondence, 1935-1944 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Site Planning Section, U.S. Housing Authority and Federal Public Housing Authority reports, 1940, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Site Planning Section, U.S. Housing Authority and Federal Public Housing Authority notes, memos, clipping, plan (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - San Juan, Puerto Rico - housing and planning correspondence, poem, pamphlet, clippings, 1942-1952 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - San Juan, Puerto Rico - housing and planning photos, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 41-42)
  - San Juan, Puerto Rico - housing and planning photos (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - San Juan, Puerto Rico- La Perla Park drawings, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Park Forest, Illinois - town plan correspondence, speech, clipping, plans, 1946-1958 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Commission of Fine Arts, Washington D.C. - Civic Art correspondence, 1950-1958 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Commission of Fine Arts, Washington D.C. - Civic Art notes, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Commission of Fine Arts speeches, transcripts, 1944-1952 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Commission of Fine Arts pamphlets, 1934-1955 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Commission of Fine Arts clippings, 1950-1962 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Harvard Lecturing Appointment correspondence, directives, 1952-1953 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Consultations - correspondence, invoices, 1952-1959 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Calixto Garcia Monument, Cuba - photos, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 53)
- Series II. Writings
  - Published Writings
    - The Central High School Monthly (Elbert Peets, editor), 1904 (Box 1, Folder 54)
    - "Street Trees in the Built-Up Districts of Large Cities" Landscape Architecture, 1915 (Box 1, Folder 55)
    - Civic Art, co-authored with Werner Hegemann - contract, correspondence, brochures, cross reference, 1921-1958 (Box 1, Folder 56)
    - Civic Art - prints, c. 1922 (Box 1, Folder 57-60)
    - Civic Art - prints, c. 1922 (Box 2, Folder 1-6)
    - Civic Art - negatives, c. 1922 (Box 2, Folder 7-39)
    - "Central Park" The American Mercury - correspondence, drafts, article, 1924-1925 (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - "Interior of the Lincoln Memorial" The American Mercury - correspondence, drafts, article, 1925 (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - "Mussolini, Haussmann, and Company" The New Republic - correspondence, articles, 1926 (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - "The New Washington" The New Republic, The American Mercury - correspondence, 1926 (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - "The Landscape Priesthood" The American Mercury - correspondence, drafts, article, 1926-1927 (Box 2, Folder 44)
    - "Restoration of Rome", 1927 (Box 2, Folder 45)
    - "Cleveland Reservoir" The Nation - correspondence, article, drawing, 1926-1927 (Box 2, Folder 46)
    - "The Reign of the Masonry Dome" The Nation - correspondence, article, 1927 (Box 2, Folder 47)
    - "The Genealogy of L'Enfant's Washington" - American Institute of Architectures - correspondence, draft, article, 1926-1927 (Box 2, Folder 48)
    - "Art is Craftsmanship" The Vista, 1927 (Box 2, Folder 49)
    - "Restraint and Order in Planning Outdoor Rooms" Your Garden, 1927 (Box 2, Folder 50)
    - "Garden Epigrams and Insults by Elbert Peets" Your Garden, 1927 (Box 2, Folder 51)
    - "The Garden as a Reservoir of Time" Your Garden, c. 1927 (Box 2, Folder 52)
    - "On the High Hedge as a Hobby for Men" Your Garden, c. 1927 (Box 2, Folder 53)
    - "Famous Town Planners: I - Haussmann" - correspondence, article, 1925-1927 (Box 2, Folder 54)
    - "Famous Town Planners: II - Camillo Sitte", 1927 (Box 2, Folder 55)
    - "Famous Town Planners: III - L'Enfant", 1927-1929 (Box 2, Folder 56)
    - "Famous Town Planners: IV - Plans for Re-building London in 1666", 1930 (Box 2, Folder 57)
    - Baltimore Sunday Sun, Washington Plan Series - correspondence, drafts, articles, 1928-1935 (Box 2, Folder 58)
    - "Current Town Planning in Washington" - correspondence, draft, article, 1931 (Box 2, Folder 59)
    - "An Accurate Re-Drawing of the Central Part of L'Enfant's Autograph Plan" Architectural Record, 1928-1932 (Box 2, Folder 60)
    - "L'Enfant's Washington" The Town Planning Review, 1933 (Box 2, Folder 61)